Guide to the Jay C. Waldman Papers, 1968-2003 AIS.2007.10
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Campaign for Governor Primary Election, 1969-1978; VI.
  - Campaign-in-Progress (CIP), 1972-1978; 5.
    Files from the progression of the primary campaign include myriad topics, events, news clippings, and results. These files together represent the multiple aspects of this and other campaigns: correspondence, previous campaign results, early "campaign binder," election documents, election results, ephemera, fundraising, lists, maps, media, news releases, politicians, polls, schedules, staff, and surrogate speakers. Significant in detail are schedules, and fundraising as well as news clippings that track the campaign. The clippings are from 1977. Those from 1978 are included in the Opposition Research series, and those for Thornburgh, in previous subseries. The remaining materials date from 1972 to 1978.
    - Correspondence, resumes, offers of help, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, congratulations, offers of help, May 1978 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence from Thornburgh for Governor, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Campaign, guidelines, organization, and articles, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Campaigns, previous election results, 1972-1976 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Campaigns, previous election results by county, 1970-1976 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Campaign binder, candidates, issues, organization, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Campaign clippings, May 1977 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Campaign clippings, June 1977 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Campaign clippings, July 1977 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Campaign clippings, August 1977 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Campaign clippings, September 1977 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Campaign clippings, October 1977 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Campaign clippings, November 1977 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Campaign clippings, December 1977 (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Campaign clippings, regarding issues, January-February, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Campaign clippings, miscellaneous, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Election Committee Documents, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Election week countdown, April-May 1978 (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Election results, May 1978 (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Fundraising, letters, drafts, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - Fundraising, GOP, August 1977 (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - Fundraising, May-October 1977 (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - Fundraising, November-December 1977 (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - Fundraising, projections and goals, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 25)
    - Fundraising, budgets and disbursements, 1977-1978 (Box 12, Folder 26)
    - Fundraising, deposit lists, July 1977-May 1978 (Box 12, Folder 27)
    - Fundraising, January-February, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 28)
    - Fundraising, March-April 1978 (Box 12, Folder 29)
    - Lists, candidates, office holders, and events, 1976-1978 (Box 12, Folder 30)
    - Maps, state and city ward maps, 1977-1978 (Box 12, Folder 31)
    - Media, Press kits, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 32)
    - Media, Sales Spot Schedule, Harrisburg, Lancaster, York, April-May 1978 (Box 12, Folder 33)
    - Media, Sales Spot Schedule, Wilkes-Barre, Scranton, April-May 1978 (Box 12, Folder 34)
    - Media, Sales Spot Schedule, Erie, April-May 1978 (Box 12, Folder 35)
    - Media, Sales Spot Schedule, Philadelphia, April-May 1978 (Box 12, Folder 36)
    - Media, Sales Spot Schedule, Pittsburgh, April-May 1978 (Box 12, Folder 37)
    - Media, Sales Spot Schedule, Johnstown, Altoona, April-May 1978 (Box 12, Folder 38)
    - Media, Spot Schedule, April-May 1978 (Box 12, Folder 39)
    - Media, Spot Schedule, April-May 1978 (Box 12, Folder 40)
    - Media, Garth media summaries, May 1978 (Box 12, Folder 41)
    - Media, JCW media buys list, radio actualities, April-May 1978 (Box 12, Folder 42)
    - Media, News releases, March-May 1978 (Box 12, Folder 43)
    - Media, Radio actualities, April-May 1978 (Box 12, Folder 44)
    - Politicians, articles, campaign brochures, news releases, 1976-1978 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Polls, pre-election, 1977-1978 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Schedules, Requests, November 1977-May 1978 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Schedules, Weekly and daily, May-December 1977 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Schedules, Long-range, July-December 1977 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Schedules, Announcement, and news release, January 10-12, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Schedules, Scheduler Seif memo, January-February 1978 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Schedules, Monthly and long-range, January-May 1978 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Schedules, Post primary plans, March 1978 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Schedules, Daily, February-March 1978 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Schedules, Daily, April-May 1978 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Speakers, Surrogate, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Staff, Exploratory Advisory Group, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Staff, Lists and event, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Staff, Campaign staff and organization, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Staff, County field organization and field reports, 1977-1978 (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - Staff, County field operations, lists, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - Staff, County field operations, overall reviews, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 18)
- Campaign for Governor General Election, 1978; VII.
  The Thornburgh general election campaign was guided again, as was the primary, by Jay Waldman's campaign plan as presented in his memoranda. This election was especially challenging considering that there was a significant Democratic registration edge. There were two noteworthy candidates, Flaherty and Thornburgh, both from Western Pennsylvania. They each were challenged to make themselves and their platforms known across the state, somewhat easier for Flaherty, who had run statewide previously for U.S. Senate, although unsuccessfully. Much campaign effort focused on the Philadelphia area, and in fact the Thornburgh headquarters moved from Pittsburgh to Philadelphia for the general election. The two Lieutenant Governor candidates, Scranton and Casey, had widely divergent backgrounds, resulting in Scranton's active participation in the campaign, and Casey scarcely any, at the request of Flaherty. Much of the information about the candidates will be found in Series IV. Campaign for Governor Opposition Research. Platform and issues can be found in Series V. Campaign Issues. There are two videos of Thornburgh campaign ads that are housed separately in media storage.
  The Flaherty campaign did not conduct as much research by far, and depended instead on Flaherty's charismatic image and mayoral reputation. Polls quietly conducted in the summer by the Thornburgh campaign placed its candidate 32 points behind Flaherty, a stunning fact that was successfully kept secret. In the fall, Thornburgh moved closer and by mid October was "merely" 12-15 points behind, a fact that the campaign vigorously declared "momentum." There were two major debates in the fall that were reported in the news to favor Thornburgh. Thornburgh's issues registered with voters and Flaherty's efforts to stay aloof from the tarnished reputation of the then Governor Shapp administration Democrats were unsuccessful. When election night came, Thornburgh was declared the victor by Walter Cronkite at 8:30 PM, joined by the other networks an hour later. There is significant additional information about this election in the Dick Thornburgh Papers. This series is further divided into four subseries: Memoranda and Notes, Fundraising, Campaign in Progress, and Polls. The material in this series all dates from the election in 1978.
  - Memoranda and Notes, 1978; 1.
    Waldman's memos spell out the campaign in remarkable detail, and were scrupulously followed. There were many who considered him inexperienced and that he would be unsuccessful. However, Waldman proved them wrong with the successful campaign. In addition to Waldman's memos, there are memoranda from Thornburgh and others. The campaign demands on candidate Thornburgh resulted in more verbal interactions from him and fewer memoranda. The Murray Dickman memos reflect the all-important field organization activity. The memos all date from 1978.
    - Memoranda from Jay Waldman, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence to/from Jay Waldman, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 20)
    - Waldman handwritten campaign notes, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 21)
    - Memoranda and correspondence to/from Dick Thornburgh, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 22)
    - Campaign memoranda from Murray Dickman, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 23)
    - Memoranda and campaign correspondence, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 24)
  - Fundraising, 1978; 2.
    Fundraising is an unavoidable and challenging process for any campaign, which was made even more difficult being that Thornburgh came from western Pennsylvania. Moving the campaign headquarters to Philadelphia was helpful, combined with effective and diligent fundraising leadership. The fact of Thornburgh's being so far behind in the summer fortunately did not become public knowledge. The point spread would have drastically and adversely affected fundraising had it been known. The fundraising material dates from 1978.
    - General election finance plan, June 6, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 25)
    - Finance committee agendas, correspondence, memos, May–October 1978 (Box 13, Folder 26)
    - Event invitations, June-October 1978 (Box 13, Folder 27)
    - Events, attendees, June-October 1978 (Box 13, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence, September-October 1978 (Box 13, Folder 29)
    - Donors, September-October 1978 (Box 13, Folder 30)
  - Campaign in Progress, 1978; 3.
    These campaign files contain topics that are illustrative of the multiple issues and challenges all campaigns address. The debate assessments and overwhelming favorable endorsements are of note. The field staff was active and their reports are very detailed. Similar topics are available in depth in the Dick Thornburgh Papers. All of the campaign in progress material dates from 1978.
    - Articles, by or about, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 31)
    - Brochures, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 32)
    - Consultants, Teeter, and Mahe, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 33)
    - County plans, Beaver, Burks, and Chester, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 34)
    - County plans, Crawford, Erie, and Fayette, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 35)
    - County plans, Clarion, Jefferson, and Potter, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 36)
    - County plans, Northumberland, Schuylkill, Westmoreland, and Venango, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 37)
    - County plans (Northwest), Elk, Forest, McKean, and Warren, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 38)
    - Debate, sponsored by League of Women Voters, October 1978 (Box 13, Folder 39)
    - Election Results, November 1978 (Box 13, Folder 40)
    - Endorsements, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 41)
    - Field Reports, May-June 1978 (Box 13, Folder 42)
    - Field Reports, July 1978 (Box 13, Folder 43)
    - Field Reports, August 1978 (Box 13, Folder 44)
    - Field Reports, September 1978 (Box 13, Folder 45)
    - Field Reports, October 1978 (Box 13, Folder 46)
    - GOP, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Media, monitoring reports, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Media, press kit, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Media, radio actualities, schedules, drafts, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Media consultant, Garth, cancelled, July, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Media consultant, Deardourff, draft agreement, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - News Releases, June 9-September 12, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - News Releases, September 14-November 5, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Polls, July, October 1978 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Schedules, DT long-range, July-October 1978 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Schedules, DT daily, May-November 1978 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Schedules, WWS long-range, September-October 1978 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Schedules, WWS daily, July-November 1978 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Speeches, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Staff, June-November, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Surrogate speakers, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Volunteer activity, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Polls, 1978; 4.
    Throughout the campaign, but especially in the summer months, the need to carefully monitor progress was essential. As Thornburgh was not well known across the state and now was opposed by Flaherty, who had previously campaigned statewide and who also had the decided advantage of far greater Democratic voter registration, meticulous polling was vital. Market Opinion Research (MOR), presented detailed information at a critical time, and in fact was used during the years of Thornburgh's governorship as well. It was during the summer that the alarming realization that Thornburgh was 30 points behind became known within the campaign. Fortunately, however, the campaign staff successfully kept this under wraps so that the essential fundraising would not be affected. Indeed as the campaign neared its end, the 15-point gap was hailed as momentum in early October, although that in itself was worrisome. These August polls and surveys provided significant guidance at a pivotal time in the campaign itself and related to fundraising. The polls material all dates from 1978.
    - PA Voting Analysis, August 1978 (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - PA Statewide Analysis, August 1978 (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Binder, PA Statewide Study, Data, August 1978 (Box 14, Folder 20)
- Gubernatorial Transition, 1978; VIII.
  On November 7, 1978, Dick Thornburgh was elected of Pennsylvania. The period of time between the election and when the Governor-elect is inaugurated is referred to as the Transition. Thornburgh's campaign staff lost no time putting together a vigorous transition team to immediately seek information about the departments of government, their shortcoming and successes. Study teams were formed, the members of which included noteworthy, knowledgeable community persons from across the state. The files documented in this series are predominately reports by study committees. These reports helped set goals and guide subsequent courses of action for the Thornburgh administration. Some additional study team reports can be found in the Dick Thornburgh Papers. The files in this subseries date from November to December, 1978.
  - "The First Six Months," Thornburgh letter to Shapp, Study committee list, 1978 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Department of State, Bureau Professional & Occupational Affairs, 1978 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Study Committee Report, Governor's Office, General Services, 1978 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Study Committee Report, Transportation, 1978 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Study Committee Report, Health, 1978 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Study Committee Report, Personnel, 1978 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Study Committee Report, Labor and Industry, 1978 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Committee Report, Education, 1978 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Study Committee Report, Community Affairs, 1978 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Study Committee Report, Commerce and Business, 1978 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Study Committee Report, DER and Energy, 1978 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Report, "Philadelphia: An Urban Strategy", November 1978 (Box 15, Folder 12)
- Re-election Campaign for Governor, 1979-1983; IX.
  This re-election campaign had many Thornburgh accomplishments to convey to the voters. However, the steel industry in Pennsylvania was deeply troubled at the time and Reagonomics at the national level was unpopular, both of which meant that Pennsylvania voters were discontented generally in 1982. Thus, a rather unknown and undistinguished one term Democrat congressman, Allen Ertel, came far closer to winning than anyone expected. The Ertel campaign pursued unwarranted issues and made many false claims about the Thornburgh administration and campaign. Despite these factors, Thornburgh won, and compared to other Republicans, he won by a larger margin than any of the others. There are three campaign videos included in this series and are housed separately in media storage. Two are Thornburgh campaign ads, and the other Ertel campaign ads. This series is further divided into four subseries: MOR polling, Thornburgh Administration Accomplishments, Ertel Opposition Research, and Campaign-in-Progress.
  - Market Opinion Research (MOR) Polling, 1982; 1.
    As a result of general voter discontent, the polling became particularly important. As can be seen in the broad in-depth studies included in this subseries and from other analyses by Jay Waldman, very close and continual attention was given to these facts and figures. The material dates from 1982.
    - Statewide Study, May 1982 (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Statewide Study, May 1982 (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - PA Survey Results, June 1982 (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - PA Statewide Governor's Data, August 1982 (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - PA Statewide Governor's Data, August 1982 (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - Statewide Statistical Summary, September 1982 (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - PA Ad Test and Thornburgh/Ertel ads compared, September 1982 (Box 15, Folder 19)
    - PA Statewide Study, September 1982 (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - PA Statewide Study, October 1982 (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - PA Statewide Study, October 1982 (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - PA Statewide Study, October 1982 (Box 15, Folder 23)
    - Post Election Study, November 1982 (Box 15, Folder 24)
  - Thornburgh Administration Accomplishments, 1979-1982; 2.
    In the first campaign for governor (1977-1978) the issues and related promises were drawn on carefully researched needs and concerns of Pennsylvanians and specific intentions to solve or reduce the attendant problems. Therefore, the administration was committed fully to following up those promises and did so successfully in many ways. Thus the enumeration of these accomplishments was an essential component of the re-election campaign. As will be seen in the endorsement files that follow in Subseries 4, the newspapers and other organizations generally and specifically agreed. The Thornburgh Administration Accomplishments date from 1979 to 1982.
    - Thornburgh Issue/Accomplishments, 1979-1982 (Box 15, Folder 25)
    - Thornburgh Issue/Accomplishments, 1979-1982 (Box 15, Folder 26)
  - Ertel Opposition Research, 1979-1982; 3.
    Always important in campaigns is the research into one's opponent, their record of accomplishments, voting records, and personal and campaign conduct. The Thornburgh campaign was particularly alert to these needs with extensive and detailed resultant information. Ertel had been in state government, but was at this time a one term U.S. Congressman. His record was not distinguished, but no stones were left unturned in his assessment. Ertel's conduct of the campaign was challenging and is documented in the following files. The first seven Folders comprise what was originally the Ertel opposition research binder put together for campaign guidance and reference. Subsequent files are additions and follow the campaign by month. The research materials date from 1979 to 1982.
    - I. Personal and campaign conduct, 1982 (Box 15, Folder 27)
    - II. Government, Economic Issues & Constituencies, 1982 (Box 15, Folder 28)
    - II. Government, Economic Issues & Constituencies, 1982 (Box 15, Folder 29)
    - III. Human Service Issues and Constituencies, 1982 (Box 15, Folder 30)
    - IV. Miscellaneous issues, 1982 (Box 15, Folder 31)
    - Appendices, 1982 (Box 15, Folder 32)
    - Ertel/ Lloyd Campaign Contributors, 1980-1982 (Box 15, Folder 33)
  - Campaign-in-Progress, 1979-1982; 4.
    This subseries contains all the aspects of a campaign from news clippings to mailings, issues, media, and in particular news releases and memoranda. The campaign updates further track the progress of the Thornburgh campaign. The "issues" included in this subseries are those that were contentious, also known as "flaps". Substantive issues are in the accomplishment files in Subseries 2. Thornburgh Administration Accomplishments. The JCW handwritten poll notes are very technical and are indicative of the time and careful analyses given the data. The voter groups and mailings represent the fundamental information provided to the Thornburgh campaign's logical constituents. The materials date from 1979 to 1982.
    - Finances, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Voting Record, 1979-1982 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Campaign organization, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Clippings, February-April, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Campaign, April-May 18, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Campaign, June-July, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Campaign, August 1982 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Campaign, September 1982 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Campaign, October 1982 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Accomplishments, Thornburgh Administration, 1979-1982 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Campaign Organization, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Clips, Thornburgh, March 1982 (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Consultant, Eddie Mahe, March-June 1982 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Debate, April-October 1982 (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Endorsements, Thornburgh, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Fundraising (GTC), October 1981-December 1982 (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - Issues, Crime/Energy, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - Issues, Thornburgh mailings contested, June-September 1982 (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - Issues, Hoffman/Taping public debate, July 1982 (Box 16, Folder 19)
    - Issues, Publication personal income taxes, September 1982 (Box 16, Folder 20)
    - Issues, Education and PSEA, 1981-1982 (Box 16, Folder 21)
    - Legal References, 1981-1982 (Box 16, Folder 22)
    - Memoranda by JCW and others, 1981-1982 (Box 16, Folder 23)
    - Media, Monitoring, September-October 1982 (Box 16, Folder 24)
    - Media, Bailey Deardourff Plan, May 1982 (Box 16, Folder 25)
    - Media, Bailey Deardourff Ads, September 1982 (Box 16, Folder 26)
    - Media, Bailey Deardourff Invoices, November 1982 (Box 16, Folder 27)
    - Media, Ads, schedules and spots, September-October 1982 (Box 16, Folder 28)
    - Media, MOR Ad Evaluation, undated (Box 16, Folder 29)
    - Media, JCW handwritten notes, September-October 1982 (Box 16, Folder 30)
    - Media, Endorsement spots, October-November 1982 (Box 16, Folder 31)
    - Media, Ad filming, July-August 1982 (Box 16, Folder 32)
    - Media, Tribute/Issue Ads, September-November 1982 (Box 16, Folder 33)
    - News Releases and campaign update memos, June-October 1982 (Box 16, Folder 34)
    - Polls, JCW handwritten calculations, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 35)
    - Polls, JCW handwritten calculations, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 36)
    - Polls, JCW handwritten calculations, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 37)
    - Voter Groups and mailings, June-September 1982 (Box 16, Folder 38)
    - Voter Groups and mailings, June-October 1982 (Box 16, Folder 39)
    - Public relations folder for press, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 40)
  - Election Results and Analyses, 1982-1983; 5.
    The final election results for both primary and general elections are documented in this subseries. However, the final field reports and analyses by MOR and JCW are particularly of interest. The Election Results and Analyses material date from 1982 to 1983.
    - Primary election results, May 1982 (Box 16, Folder 41)
    - General election results, November 1982 (Box 16, Folder 42)
    - Final field reports and campaign sign-off, November-December 1982 (Box 16, Folder 43)
    - MOR Post-Election Analysis, November 1982 (Box 16, Folder 44)
    - JCW post election survey and analysis, April 1983 (Box 16, Folder 45)
    - Election Contributions, final, April 15, 1983 (Box 16, Folder 46)
- Office of the Governor, 1979-1986; X.